Guide to the Herbert H. Lehman papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series IV: Clipping Books, Press Releases, Speeches Articles and Statements
  - Subseries IV.6: Press Releases
    - Statements, speeches, background information; in chronological order., (10 drawers)
- Series V: Miscellaneous Papers
  - Subseries V.1: Personal Family Papers
    - Family marriage certificates, notebooks, family trees, and printed souvenirs. 1856-1961
  - Subseries V.2: College Themes
    - About sixteen original manuscripts (100 pages) in cellophane envelopes. Typed copies are also in the file. Much of the material is on topics which held Herbert Lehman's lifelong attention, for example: The Education Test in Immigration Notes... on Changing the Present Method of Elections The Political Aspect of Europe, 1898 & 1899, (1 looseleaf notebook)
  - Subseries V.3: Armed Forces Scrapbook
    - Letters, carbon copies, official forms and papers, news clippings, and photographs. A complete history of Herbert Lehman's military service, 1917-1963, (1 leather-bound folio scrapbook)
  - Subseries V.4: Guest Lists and Entertainment
    - Complete list of all social and official entertainment and of invited guests, with addresses of guests and notations of which invitations they received, 1933-1942, (5 looseleaf )
  - Subseries V.5: Honorary Memberships
    - Correspondence concerning all honorary memerships accepted or rejected during this period; arranged chronologically, 1933-1942, (1 drawer)
  - Subseries V.6: Birthday and Other Greetings Received
    - Sixtieth birthday, 1938 Seventieth birthday, 1948 Seventy-fifth birthday, 1953 Retirement from the Senate, 1956-1957 Eightieth birthday, 1958 Recovery from illness, 1963 Eighty-fifth birthday, 1963, 1938-1963, (2 drawers)
  - Subseries V.7: Invitations
    - All invitations received during this period, separated into folders by month and further separated as "accepted" and "declined.", 1950-1963, (6 drawers)
  - Subseries V.8: Appointment Diaries
    - A ten-year record of daily appointments, 1954-1963, (10 volumes)
  - Subseries V.9: Democratic Advisory Council
    - Collection of notices, releases, letters to directors, etc., 1956-1960, (1 looseleaf notebook)
  - Subseries V.10: Condolences
    - Messages received by the family at the time of Herbert Lehman's death. A card index file notes names and addresses of all correspondents, 1964, (1 drawer, 2 card index boxes)
- Series VI: The Reference Library of The Herbert H. Lehman Papers
  The Herbert H. Lehman Papers have their own reference library which includes all books and articles by or about Herbert Lehman, as well as a large collection of inscribed presentation copies of books by colleagues and friends.
  All the basic reference works covering the Governorship years and the Senate years are at hand for use with the Papers.
  A section of the reference library is devoted to materials by and about the Lehman family. It includes a complete collection of the legal and other writings of Arthur Lehman Goodhart, K.B.E. (gift of Professor Goodhart, 1967), and a good number of works by or about Chief judge Irving Lehman.
  The Library includes numerous reference works on special subjects. Included in this category is a set of card index reference cards entitled "The Impact of the State Defense Board on Civil Rights in New York. Gift of Dominic J. Capeci, Jr., 1968.
  - Subseries VI.1: Working Papers fot the Nevins Biography
    - Among the most valuable items in the reference library, in addition to the Papers themselves, are the complete working reference files, drafts, manuscripts,. page and galley proofs, notes, memoranda, and correspondence connected with the writing of Herbert Lehman and His Era by Allan Nevins. Included in this collection is the original typescript, with drafts and memoranda, {New York], [ca. 1963], (3 drawers, 3 card index drawers, 3 folio-size looseleaf notebooks, 8 manuscript boxes)
      [Gift of Professor Nevins, 1967]
  - Subseries VI.2: Working Papers for the Shannon Biography
    - The complete research file and projected chapters of the biography of Herbert Lehman by William V. Shannon which was never completed, (1 drawer)
      [Gift of William V. Shannon, 1955]
  - Subseries VI.3: Reference Works on the Governorship: A Selection of Titles
    - The Public Papers of Governor Herbert H. Lehman, 1933-1942 10 volumes: Sate of New York Executive Budget, 1932-1943 22 volumes -- The Legislative Manual of the State of New York, 1929-1942 14 volumes -- The New York Red Book, 1929, 1932, 1933, 1934, 1936 5 volumes -- The New York State Constitutional Convention Committee, 1938 12 volumes -- Record of Vote Cast for Herbert H. Lehman, 1928-1938 -- Record of Vote Cast for Herbert H. Lehman, 1928-1934 -- New York State Legislative Programs. 1933-1942 10 volumes
  - Subseries VI.4: Reference Works of the Senatorship: A Selectionb of Titles
    - The Congressional Record, Volumes 96-102, 1950-1956 103 volumes: Proceedings and Reports, 82nd-84th Congresses: covers all committees of which Senator Lehman was a member: Labor and Public Welfare, Banking and Currency, etc. 72 volumes -- The Congressional Directory, 1952-1956 5 volumes
  - Subseries VI.5: UNRRA Publications: A Selection of Titles
    - Journals of the Council Sessions, 1943-1946. 6 volumes -- The History of UNRRA, edited by George Woodbridge. 3 volumes
  - Subseries VI.6: Oral History
    - The Oral History Collection of Columbia University has made available to researchers using the Herbert H. Lehman Papers "The Herbert H. Lehman Oral History" (800 pages) and "The Oral History Memoirs of Herbert H. Lehman by His Associates". The following friends and associates were interviewed for the Memoirs: Helen (Mrs. Frank) Altschul 13 pages -- Emanuel Celler 3 pages -- Paul Douglas 22 pages -- Julius C. C. Edelstein 45 pages -- James A. Farley 44 pages -- Carolin Flexner 67 pages -- Hubert H. Humphrey 25 pages -- Estes Kefauver 12 pages -- George Meany 13 pages -- Henry Morgenthau, Jr. 8 pages -- Wayne Morse 92 pages -- Charles Poletti 32 pages -- Eleanor Roosevelt 17 pages -- Anna M. Rosenberg 14 pages -- Samuel 1. Rosenman 23 pages -- Marc Tanenbaum 38 pages -- Roy Wilkins 26 pages.
      The attention of researchers is drawn to the many other oral histories which are not specifically part of the Herbert H. Lehman project but which contain valuable information on the man and his times. Inquiries concerning this group of memoirs should be made directly to the Oral History Research Office, 801 Butler Library, Columbia University, New York, N.Y. 10027. The following sample list illustrates the variety of memoirs available: Chester Bowles -- James B. Carey -- William Hammatt Davis -- James A. Farley -- Edward Flynn -- Homer Folks -- Felix Frankfurter -- Paul G. Hoffman -- Philip C. Jessup -- Lithgow Osborne -- Herbert W. Parisius -- Frances Perkins -- Louis H. Pink -- Jacob S. Potofsky -- Lindsay Rogers -- Samuel 1. Rosenman -- Francis B. Sayre -- George S. Van Schaick -- Roy Wilkins -- Robert E. Wood
- Series VII: Films, Tapes And Disk recordings
  - Subseries VII.1: Films
    - The Herbert H. Lehman Papers include an invaluable collection of moving pictures of Herbert Lehman's political life and of occasions with his family and friends. There are both silent and sound films, available for showing in The Lehman Suite, 1928-1963, (ca. 60 reels)
  - Subseries VII.2: Disc Recordings
    - The discs are in various sizes and play at various speeds, 1933-1966, (200+ recordings)
      [Some of the discs were presented by Morris S. Novik, 1967]
  - Subseries VII.3: Tapes
    - The tapes, as well as the discs, record speeches, statements, mem- orial addresses, and campaign material. Included through the courtesy of Governor Charles Poletti and Roy Wilkins are taped interviews concerning the study entitled "The Impact of the State Defense Board on Civil Rights in New York, 1939-1942.", 1950-1965, (ca. 50 reels)
      [See also IV. The Reference Library of the Herbert H. Lehman Papers). This Part of the collection also includes material presented by Morris S. Novik, 1967, and Dominic J. Capeci, Jr., 1968.]
- Series VIII: Memorabilia
  There is a large and interesting collection of memorabilia with the Herbert H. Lehman Papers. A great deal of it is on permanent display in the Lehman Suite
  The memorabilia includes Herbert Lehman's American and foreign medals and decorations, certificates of appointments and memberships, testimonial certificates and presentations, an extensive collection of photographs, and a large number of other inter esting objects. There is a fine collection of original drawings of political cartoons connected with Herbert Lehman's career, including many by Herblock and Rollin Kirby. A portrait of Governor Lehman painted by an inmate of a state prison, which is typical of the material presented to public figures, is part of this collection. Loaned by the State of New York Department of General Services
  - The entire collection of memorabilia is catalogued